Guide to the Richard Courant Papers MC 150
New York University Archives
Richard Courant Papers
1902-1972
MC 150
New York University Archives
33.0 linear feet [97 boxes]
Richard Courant developed New York University's graduate program in mathematics and established the Institute for Mathematical Sciences, later named for him. The collection spans the entire length of Courant's career as a mathematician from his student days in Germany to his work at NYU. It includes administrative and personal correspondence, published works as well as lecture material.
Biographical Note
Richard Courant, pioneer in applied mathematics and intellectual architect of NYU's Courant Institute for Mathematical Sciences, was born into a Jewish family in Lublinitz, Germany (now Poland) in 1888. He was academically-minded from an early age. Courant studied physics and mathematics at the University of Breslau and the University of Zürich before ultimately finding his niche at the University of Göttingen. There he quickly became part of a group of renowned mathematicians, physicists and philosophers.
At Göttingen, Courant became the protégé of mathematician David Hilbert, completing his dissertation on the Dirihlet Principle there in 1910. Courant spent two years lecturing at Göttingen after completing compulsory military service. He married Nelly Neumann, a student he knew from his time at Breslau, in 1912. They divorced during Courant's time in combat during World War I.
On the outbreak of the war, Courant, immediately enlisted in the army. In 1915, while serving on the front lines, he was severely wounded near Douai, France. While in the trenches Courant realized the need for more reliable military communication, and conceived of a telegraph system that would use the earth as its wire. He spent the rest of the war developing and implementing such a system with a team of scientists at Göttingen. At that time he also met Nerina (Nina) Runge, the daughter of the famous Göttingen math professor Carl Runge. They wed in 1919 and remained married until Courant’s death in 1972. They had four children.
After World War I, Courant taught briefly at the University of Münster before returning to Göttingen as a full professor, where he worked to strengthen the mathematics department. He continued his work in partial differential equations and mathematical physics, publishing widely. Perceiving a need for advanced texts in various mathematical topics, Courant began editing a series of monographs in partnership with publisher Ferdinand Springer. Grundlehren der mathematischen Wissenschaften is still published to this day.
With the help of the Rockefeller Foundation, in 1929 Courant organized the construction of a new building to house the university's mathematics institute. This helped further the institute's long-standing goal of promoting collaboration between Göttingen‘s math and scientific communities. This international partnership was an early indication of Courant's talent for leadership in an academic setting. The Nazis' rise to power meant disaster for the math and science communities in German universities. Under the "Civil Service Law," Jewish and politically suspect professors were summarily dismissed from their positions. As a consequence, Courant was placed on "extended leave" from Göttingen in 1933. He tried many times to fight his dismissal, but realized it was futile. He quickly obtained a one-year position at the University of Cambridge.
Courant's colleagues Niels and Harald Bohr and Abraham Flexner helped him secure a two-year teaching position at NYU in 1934. At that time the university’s math program was small and underdeveloped. "New York," Courant said in a 1967 speech accepting NYU’s Gallatin Medal for outstanding achievement, "seemed starved for mathematical activity." Moreover, the Great Depression meant the university’s resources were drastically limited. Becoming head of the Graduate School’s Department of Mathematics in 1936, Courant slowly grew the program. He sought financial help from external sources such as the Carnegie and Rockefeller Foundations. Over the next decade he brought in K.O. Friedrichs and Fritz John, who had studied and taught with him in Germany. He complemented their talent with the American mathematician J.J. Stoker. Courant, Stoker and Friedrichs quickly formed the core of the department and strove towards broadening its focus by bridging the gap between theoretical and applied mathematics. He became an American citizen in 1940.
The influence of Courant's cohort of mathematicians at NYU was still relatively small when the United States entered World War II. Courant secured government funding for various military projects to help the war effort. This work increased NYU’s prominence in applied mathematics and for the first time brought the government's attention to the group of talented mathematicians Courant had gathered. Funded mainly by the Navy and the Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD), the department researched wave propagations, detonations and other military-related phenomena. Through this work Courant was invited to become a member of the OSRD's Applied Mathematics Panel, headed by Warren Weaver. The panel provided mathematical support to scientists involved in military work. Courant worked closely with Warren Weaver, who headed the Mathematics Panel of the ORSD, to secure even more war project funding and expand the faculty.
Military funding continued to flow in the immediate postwar years. In 1951, NYU's Board of Trustees approved Courant's proposal for a mathematics institute to be supported by outside funders. Initially called the Institute for Mathematics and Mechanics, its name was changed to the Institute of Mathematical Sciences (IMS) to reflect the broad nature of its work. The Institute was devoted to all areas of mathematics, recognizing no boundary between applied and theoretical work. Courant served as its first director. Soon after, the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission established a computing center at the university. The center was built around a UNIVAC I computer, the first commercially available computer in the United States.
Courant retired from teaching in 1958, receiving an honorary degree at NYU's commencement that year, but continued his consulting work. The IMS was renamed the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences (CIMS) three years later. Soon after, the Sloan Foundation, Ford Foundation and the National Science Foundation provided funding for a new home for the institute.
Warren Weaver Hall was completed in 1965. Courant stayed on as a consultant for the Institute until his death in 1972.
Courant's principal works include Methods of Mathematical Physics, Vol. I and II (with David Hilbert), Differential and Integral Calculus, Vol. I and II and What is Mathematics? (with H.E. Robbins).
Scope and Contents
Approximately two-thirds of Series I and one-quarter of Series II is in German. After most of the collection was processed, the boxes were examined by an Archives staff member proficient in German. Notes on much of the German material can be found in the Container Listing at the folder-level.
Series I contains the earliest material in the collection and is mostly correspondence. The bulk of the series spans the years 1900-1940, covering Courant's time as a young student to his immigration to the U.S., but also includes files from around the time of his death. The series contains materials on Courant's schooling in Germany, including diplomas, certificates and records of his coursework as well as documents from his time in the German Army during World War I. These include trench maps and a certificate for a war service medal. Much of the series consists of correspondence with colleagues at the University of Göttingen, their articles and dissertations. The letters pertain to mathematics at Göttingen, the affects of the Nazi regime on academia and mathematics and other personal matters. Courant's move from Germany to the U.S. is also documented in this series.
Some material in Series I was used by Courant biographer Constance Reid. This is indicated by folder-level notes.
Series II, which contains a wide range of material, represents the bulk of the collection. It is largely comprised of correspondence with American, German and international colleagues, many of whom Courant tried to help secure relocation and employment at various U.S. universities during the Nazi era. Correspondence is typically filed under the correspondent's name or by the first letter of the surname.
Many of Courant's publications, lecture material and articles are also scattered throughout this series. Material related to his book publishing, translation, rights and written critiques from readers and mathematicians are included as well. Publisher Springer-Verlag, and specifically Ferdinand Springer, figures prominently in this area.
The collection details the full length of Courant's career at NYU. Administrative correspondence documents the growth of the Department of Mathematics and assembly of its faculty from Courant's closest colleagues and its evolution into the Institute for Mathematics and Mechanics and then into the Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences.
Courant and the IMS's World War II and post-war government consulting work is also well-represented in the collection, especially his work with the Atomic Energy Commission, the Office of Naval Research and IBM. Courant also spent the post-war period working to build a relationship between American and Soviet mathematicians and scientists. Correspondence and information about Soviet-American conferences are found in the collection as well. The material also reflects Courant's membership in the Mathematical Association of America, National Academy of Sciences, National Philosophical Society, Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. and the Cosmos Club.
The Courant Papers notably contains correspondence to and from Albert Einstein, Harald and Niels Bohr, Max Born, Fritz John, J.J. Stoker, K.O. Friedrichs, Abraham Flexner, Edward Teller and J. Robert Oppenheimer as well as many others.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series. The first two are based on the location of the material prior to arriving at the University Archives. Series I contains material from the home of Courant's son Ernst, while Series II is from Courant's office. The original folder titles were mostly maintained.
Series I arrived at the University Archives with some semblance of an order. Correspondence was distinctly labeled as such and generally kept alphabetical. The present organization of this series was devised to reflect the original order of the material and the alphabetical nature of Series II.
Folders labeled correspondence were organized into their own series. The rest of the material was organized into subject files and arranged alphabetically. In many cases subject files already had folder titles.
As indicated, the material in Series II was originally organized alphabetically by correspondents’ names and subjects. The original order of the material was almost always preserved, though folders and files were occasionally reorganized or renamed when necessary. Material at the end of this series marked "Grants" was made its own subseries.
Series III contains material separated because of its larger size.
Material from the Home of Ernst Courant (Subseries A: Correspondence, Subseries B: Subject Files)
Material from the Office of Richard Courant (Subseries A: General Files, Subseries B: Grants)
Oversize Material
Separated Materials
A plaque with Friedrich Leo on it has been moved to memorabilia collection. Maps depicting World War I trenches and earth telegraph testing grounds have been relocated to oversize flat storage. Documents including Courant's educational certificates as well as the certificate for the Military Merit Cross Courant received in 1916 were moved to Box 96. An issue of the newspaper Die Rote Fahne was also removed to flat file storage. See folder-level notes for original location of these materials.
Photos of the IMS offices at 25 Waverly Place have been moved to the photo collection.
Access Restrictions
This collection contained a large amount of typed correspondence printed on extremely brittle paper. In most cases, preservation photocopies replace the originals, which were discarded except when they contained signficant handwritten marks.
There are four German copies of Methods of Mathematical Physics Vol. II in the collection. They are all printed on brittle paper. An access copy of the book was made from the only complete copy of the book in the collection. Two copies are annotated and all annotations have been copied and made available to researchers. A fourth copy, incomplete and without annotations, was not copied. The originals have been restricted for preservation purposes. The copies and originals are housed in Boxes 61-63, including a box numbered 62b.
Aleksandrov, P. S., (Pavel Sergeevich), 1896-1982; Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.; American Mathematical Society.; Argonne National Laboratory.; Artin, Emil, 1898-1962; Bohr, Harald August, 1887-1951; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962; Born, Max, 1882-1970; Brandt, Leo, 1908-1971; Brookhaven National Laboratory.; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955; Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences.; Courant, Richard, 1888-1972; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Flexner, Abraham, 1866-1959; Ford Foundation.; Friedrichs, K. O., (Kurt Otto), 1901-1983; Grad, Harold, 1923-1986; Heald, Henry T., (Henry Townly), 1904-1975; Institute for Advanced Study. (Princeton, N.J.); International Business Machines Corporation.; International Congress of Mathematicians.; Interscience Publishers.; John Wiley & Sons.; John, Fritz, 1910-1994; Joint Soviet-American Symposium on Partial Differential Equations. (1963: Novosibirsk, R.S.F.S.R.).; Kinzel, Augustus B., 1900-1987; Kline, Morris, 1908-1992; Lax, Peter D.; Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory.; McShane, E. J., (Edward James), 1904-1989; Morse, Marston, 1892-1977; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.).; National Co-ordinating Committee for Aid to Refugees and Emigrants Coming from Germany.; National Science Foundation (U.S.).; Neugebauer, O., (Otto), 1899-1990; Newsom, Carroll Vincent, 1904-; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967; Rees, Mina Spiegel, 1902-1997; Richtmyer, Robert D.; Robbins, Herbert, 1915–2001; Siegel, Carl Ludwig, 1896–1981; Springer-Verlag.; Stoker, J. J., (James Johnston), 1905-1992; Teller, Edward, 1908-2003; Toeplitz, Otto, 1881-1940; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; United States. Office of Naval Research.; Universität Göttingen.; Veblen, Oswald, 1880-1960; Weaver, Warren, 1894-1978; Weyl, Hermann, 1885-1955; Applied mathematics.; Cold War; Mathematical physics; Mathematicians |x German; Mathematicians |x Russian; Mathematics |x Study and teaching |z United States; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945 |x Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Series I: Files from the Home of Ernst Courant, 1907-1969
  - Subseries A: Correspondence
    - Correspondence, ca. 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Materials related to Courant's schooling, 1905-1910; incl. Courant’s certificate from completion from gymnasium (secondary school) in Breslau, materials related to his studies at the gymnasium and various universities he attended, such as Zürich and Göttingen.
    - (Official) Correspondence (with Prussian Education Ministry), 1918, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes official patent allowing Courant to use the title "Professor," dated January 8, 1918, and correspondence to/from the Prussian Ministry of Science, Art, and National Education, 1920-1921 re: Courant's appointments at Münster and Göttingen.
    - Correspondence with Harald Bohr, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      General note
      Includes correspondence with E.M. Wright, Nina Courant (and children), Herbert Busemann, Willy Feller, Otto Neugebauer, Franz Rellich, Carl Siegel, Max Dehn, Fritz John, Karl Friedrichs (father of K. O. Friedrichs), Erwin Schoedinger, Anna Essinger, James Franck, Adriaan Fokker, Friedrich "Fritz" Courant, and Hans Bolza
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes correspondence with Carl Siegel, Louis J. Mordell, Erich Bessel-Hagen, Wilhelm Cauer, Hermann Thiersch, Adolf Windaus, Ferdinand Springer
    - Correspondence, 1920, 1937, 1946-1947, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes correspondence with Carl Still, Käthe Hilbert, Gaston Julia, Helmut Ulm, Nellie Friedrichs
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence with William Feller, Werner Fenchel, Otto Neugebauer
    - Correspondence--50th Birthday, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence with Otto Neugebauer, Carl Siegel, Max Dehn, Ernst Hellinger, Paul Epstein, Harald Bohr, Niels Bohr, Werner Fenchel, Jakob Nielsen, Niels Norlund, Emil and Natascha Artin, Edmund Landau, William Feller, Carl Still, Issai Schur
    - Correspondence, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence with Wilbur Tisdale, Max Dehn, James Franck, Ferdinand Springer, Harald Bohr, Otto Blumenthal, Bela Kerekjarto, copy of a 1934 letter from Gustav Doetsch to Erhard Tornier, materials dealing with Courant’s exemption from the emigration tax,
    - Correspondence, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence--80th Birthday, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence re: "the aunts", 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Contains letters about Courant's aunts (from his wife's family) who remained in Germany during World War II
    - Correspondence on Germany, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Correspondence about Germany after 1946, including long letter from Courant's brother-in-law, Wilhelm Runge about Germany directly after WWII as well as incomplete letter from B. L. van der Waerden
    - Correspondence ("for Nina"), 1948, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Correspondence with Carl Siegel, Pavel Alexandroff & others, including son-in-law Jürgen Moser
    - Correspondence: A, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Correspondence with Pavel Alexandroff, R. C. Archibald, the German Automobile Association, and others
    - Correspondence: A-F, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Correspondence used by Constance Reid in her Courant biography, including letters organizing Courant's stay at Cambridge in 1934, as well as several letters from future Nazi Wilhelm Blaschke
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Correspondence to/from Academic Assistance Council, Pavel Alexandroff, Bruno Amerant, American Mathematical Society, Martha Anderson and R.C. Archibald.
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Correspondence to/from N.M. Basu, Lulu von Bechtolsheim, Winthrop Bell and Ilse Benfey
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Correspondence to/from Peter Gabriel Bermann, Arnold Berliner, L. Berwald, Abram Besicovitch, Eric Bessel-Hagen, Albert Betz, George Birkoff, Wilhelm Blaschke, Otto Blumenthal, Arthur Boehm and F. Bohnenblust
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Corresondence to/from Harald Bohr, Niels Bohr, Hans Bolza, Alfred Brauer and Richard Brauer
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1934-1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Misc. correspondence
    - Correspondence: B (1 of 2), 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Includes correspondence with Nellie Bruell (wife of K.O. Friedrichs) and her father re: Friedrichs and Bruell's emigration to the United States, 1936
    - Correspondence: B (2 of 2), 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence with Herbert Busemann, Max Born, and Hedi Born
    - Correspondence: A-B, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes copies of outgoing correspondence to Richard Brauer and Herbert Busemann (see Box 2, Folders 5 and 7 for originals)
    - Correspondence: A-E (1 of 2), 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence with Emil Artin, Erich Bessel-Hagen, Herbert Beyer (Courant’s lawyer in Germany during the 1930s), and Harald Bohr
    - Correspondence: A-E (2 of 2), 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes correspondence with Niels (& Margrethe) Bohr, Hans Bolza, Herbert Busemann, Jesse Douglas, Albert Einstein
    - Correspondence: A-G (1 of 2), 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Includes correspondence with Hel Braun, Vannevar Bush, and K.O. Friedrichs
    - Correspondence: A-G (2 of 2), 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes correspondence with Aage Bohr (son of Niels Bohr), Margrethe Bohr (wife of Niels Bohr), Max Born, Pavel Alexandroff, Hedi Born, Heinrich Behnke, and the Atomic Energy Commission re: Fermi Award
    - Correspondence: B (1 of 3), 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Includes correspondence with Wilhelm Blaschke, Otto Blumenthal, and Hans Bolza
    - Correspondence: B (2 of 3), 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes correspondence with Fritz Baade, Reinhold Baer, Heinrich Behnke, Winthrop Bell, University of California, Berkeley re: Courant teaching there summer 1932, Paul Bernays, Felix Bernstein, Sergei Bernstein, Abram Besicovitch, Erich Bessel-Hagen, and Ludwig Bieberbach
    - Correspondence: B (3 of 3), 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes correspondence with Max and Hedi Born, Alfred Brauer, Richard Brauer, Alfred Busemann, Herbert Busemann, and Vannevar Bush
    - Correspondence: Benfey, Ilse, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Bernays, Paul, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Beyer, Herbert - Göttingen, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes materials dealing with compensation from the German government for Courant’s wrongful termination from the University of Göttingen in 1933
    - Correspondence: Blackie & Son, 1933-1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Blackie & Son, 1933-1944 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Blackie & Son, 1933-1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence: Blackie & Son, 1955-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence: Blake, Whitney (see "Oxford University Press"), 1961-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Blumenthal, Otto, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Bohr, Harald, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Material used by Constance Reid
    - Correspondence: Bohr, Harald, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Includes correspondence with Harald Bohr as well as a copy of Bohr's 1934 article (in Danish) from the "Berlingske Akten" criticizing Ludwig Bieberbach's attempts to "Aryanize" German mathematics.
    - Correspondence: Born, Max and Heidi, 1937-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence: C, 1929-1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Includes correspondence with Constantin Caratheodory, Wilhelm Cauer, Stefan Cohn-Vossen, and Harald Cramer
    - Correspondence: C-G, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Includes correspondence with J.R. Carson (Bell Laboratories), Walter Cahn, and Courant's cousin Erich Courant
    - Correspondence: C-G, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Includes correspondence with son Ernst, brother Fritz and mother Martha Courant as well as Hans Reich, Arthur Boehm, and Harald Cramer. Contains a copy of Martha Courant's last will and testament.
    - Correspondence: C-G, 1934-1936 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Includes correspondence with Harold Davenport, Max and Helmut Dehn, communication with UC Berkeley re: possible appointment there in 1934, Courant’s official letter of resignation from the Deutsche Mathematische Vereinigung (German Mathematical Society), and correspondence with the University of Göttingen re: Courant's pension after his forced retirement
    - Correspondence: C-G, 1934-1936 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes correspondence with Gustav Doetsch, Jesse Douglas, Arnold Dresden, as well as official correspondence with the Landesfinanzamt Hannover re: Courant’s bank accounts and money in Germany